[SQUEAKING]
[RUSTLING]
[CLICKING]
KIKI GUTIERREZ: My name is Kiki.
I'm visiting a
scholar here at MIT.
I'm actually an
assistant professor
at Polytechnical
University of Madrid.
My background is
actually on engineering.
I am aerospace engineer.
I did my PhD on numerical
methods, but after my postdoc,
I decided to start doing things
that really fascinates me,
and that's how I end up doing
something related with music.
So I'm relatively
new in this field.
Today I'm going to show you
an algorithm that I came up
for pattern detection
in music, which
is what I've been working on
for the last year and a half,
more or less.
So as running example,
I'm going to use
the most listened song of the
history, which is Baby Shark.
So I don't know
if I can play it.
At least, it's the most listened
song of the history of YouTube.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Baby shark doo doo
doo doo doo doo.
Baby Shark doo doo
Baby shark.
Mommy shark doo doo doo doo doo.
Mommy shark doo doo doo doo.
Mommy shark--
OK, is pretty much
like that of the song.
This is the melody.
So what's the problem of
pattern detection in music?
We would like to have a
tool, an automated tool that
helps us to identify over
the score or over a corpus
the important musical
ideas there, you know.
So I'm highlighting
here some fragments,
how I look first at the
blue fragment over there.
There are three fragments,
three occurrences of them.
All of them are
exactly the same.
They have the same notes
with the same pitches
and same durations.
The only difference
is that they occur
at different moments of the
score, but it seems logical.
It seems reasonable to group
them as the same musical idea
and say that they
represent the same pattern.
We can call them--
we can put them a
label, blue pattern.
For the green one,
it's a little trickier
because the occurrence number
2 and the occurrence number 3
are exactly the same.
Probably makes sense
to group them together.
Occurrence number 1
has different durations
for the notes and the
occurrence number 4
is even trickier because they
just start with the rest that--
it's three notes
also and the lyrics.
But it's pretty different.
So that's one of the main
difficulties of the problem
of pattern mining in music.
That even though objects that
we want to group together--
because in our mind represent
the same musical idea--
over the table, they might
look pretty different.
And there are two
mechanisms involved here.
The first one is something
that we have already
studied, transformations.
So if we have a
music fragment, if we
apply a mathematical
transformation over the notes
there, we obtain other fragments
that under some circumstances,
our mind will process
them as equivalent.
And how to deal with
this computationally
from the point of view of
pattern mining algorithms?
My approach was to use
the concept of viewpoint.
I'm going to show you an
example of what is this about,
but for the moment,
it's enough to know
that it has a double task.
On the first hand,
it directly takes
into account these
transformations.
You will see it in a minute.
And probably more important, it
simplifies the representation,
because one of the constants in
this course, in these classes,
is that music is
something complex.
It has complex,
logical structures
among the elements of the score.
And if we find a way to
simplify that representation,
would be helpful from the
computational point of view.
So the viewpoint representation
is pretty simple.
It's just I'm
going to substitute
a complex tune like this one by
a single sequence of symbols.
So actually, here I'm showing
three viewpoints representation.
The pitch viewpoint, it's the
sequence of these symbols 83,
83, 83, 85.
It's the midi Note.
Then we have the duration
and the onset time.
I'm going to
highlight a fragment.
So you can see the different
viewpoints representations
for that fragment.
And it's nice that the
idea of constructing
the score by overlapping
layers of information.
That's the idea.
Formerly, a viewpoint
is a mapping
between the current event, the
current time slice, and all
the former ones into symbol,
usually an integer or float
but could be others.
Those that are
derived at viewpoints.
And perhaps for your own
particular music application,
you need to develop your own
viewpoint representation.
And here is clearly highlighted
how the transformations
could be directly taken into
account by using this technique.
For instance, if you apply
the octave transformation
to that pattern
there, that fragment,
you obtain that one over there,
which by the interval viewpoint
representation, we
have the same symbol.
So for sure, any
pattern mining algorithm
that is trying to
find this sequence
will see that that
one is the same.
Is that enough to deal with
the concept of dissimilarity
in music?
Unfortunately, no.
So have a look at these two
occurrences of the green pattern
of Baby Shark.
There is no viewpoint
representation
that can take us from
one to the other.
So someone said
at some point, OK,
it would be nice to
have a kind of measure,
a mathematical tool that help
us to evaluate how different two
fragments are.
Like the aim here is that,
OK, if I use that matrix
with this guy and this guy,
I would expect a lower value
than the one that
I would obtain when
taking this guy and this guy.
Because they are more far.
They represent further ideas.
So in computer science, they
use what is called the distance
functions.
This in a general scenario is
that you can give to a function
two objects, two random objects,
for instance, me, myself,
and this computer,
and it returns
a non-negative real
number, evaluating
the degree of dissimilarity
between the two objects.
In the context of
sequences, because we
are using viewpoint
representation,
so now this fragment
will be a sequence.
For instance.
Let's think that I'm using
the duration viewpoint.
So in the literature, we have
plenty of distance functions.
This was a very trending topic
in music information retrieval
15 years ago, more or less.
There were many
studies and papers
trying to figure out which was
the best distance function,
depending on the style.
The Levenshtein distance
function, perhaps, it's
not the most advanced
one, but this
is one of the simplest one and
probably the most used one.
And it accounts for the number
of substitutions, deletions,
or insertions to go from
one sequence to the other.
So to go from the sequence 0.5,
0.5, 0.5 to the sequence 0.5,
0.52, we just need a
single substitution.
So the Levenshtein distance
function between the fragment
2 and fragment 4 is 1.
Probably the Levenshtein
distance function between this
guy and this guy it's--
I don't know-- two
or three, at least.
So cool.
Now we have all the
ingredients needed
to understand the inputs
and outputs of my algorithm.
We have a corpus or
a piece of music.
We have also the
viewpoint representation
that the user wants to choose.
And some parameters
at the input.
The minimum support is the
minimum number of repetitions
that we require to a pattern
to be considered frequent
and to be included
in the result list.
These two guys, the minimum
length and maximum length,
are the parameters to control
the lengths of the patterns
that we want to mine
and some parameters
to control the degree
of dissimilarity
from the former slide.
And the result is just like
the list of frequent patterns
together with the position.
This is an example with the
piece of the former slide.
Now I'm selecting the interval
viewpoint and those parameters
over there.
And this is an example of the
output that we might obtain.
So we have a yellow pattern
that has four occurrences
and have a look that
each of these fragments
are at most distance one
from any of the rest,
taking the Levenshtein
distance function.
And we might have,
for instance, also
this guy, the purple
pattern, and this green one,
which is of length 4.
So in a real case,
the pattern structure
might be complex, as
you see, because you
have nested patterns.
You have many overlappings.
I won't go into
the details of how
I implemented the algorithm,
just a brief overview.
I divided in four steps.
The one is the creation
of an initial database.
A vertical database
is called sometimes,
where I just take a sliding
window of minimum length,
the minimum length
selected by the user,
and I just create a
database of all the patterns
together with their
positions within the score.
Then in the next step,
I compare every pattern
against all the rest, trying
to see if they satisfies
the distance constraint.
And in that case, I
group them together
into what I call metric
patterns, which are like groups
of fragments of music.
At this stage,
it's safe to delete
the entries that doesn't reach
the minimum support constraint.
They don't have
enough occurrences
to be considered frequent.
And finally, as here, I
still have patterns of length
equal to the minimum
length, and we actually
want longer patterns.
So the last stitch is
overlapping different patterns
to form longer ones.
And to finish this I'm going
to show you some results.
This is the last slide.
I'm actually already using this.
I started collaborating
with these research groups
like seven months ago.
This is a research group from
another university of Madrid.
They got a good amount of
money of the European Union
to study the Italian operas.
They have a huge database with
many features for each piece.
And in particular, they are
interested in the motion
that the piece evokes.
So here, we are trying
to find some correlations
between the emotions and
the pattern structure
of the different pieces.
These two other products
are pretty similar.
The number 2 is on a corpus of
folk music from a very concrete
region of Europe,
around the Pyrenees,
and the second one is the
database of jazz solos.
So here we are building
classifiers, similar to what
we did in the last class.
Here I'm showing the number
of patterns per style
for the different
styles in this corpus,
but perhaps here, we can see
a cool thing of the algorithm.
That it returns also the
position of the patterns,
not only the fact that a
piece contains the pattern.
So here, I'm plotting--
it's called coverage,
this variable,
but it's actually like
the probability function
of encountering a
pattern within a solo.
So I normalize the length
of all the solos by style,
and the thin line is the
average for the solos.
We can see, for instance, that
the concentration of patterns
tends to be at the beginning
and not in the end.
This is intuitive because
the improvisers usually
start their solos in
a more organized way,
taking thematic material
from the original melody,
and then they start to
do more crazy stuff.
Then, I'm also trying
to build up a pattern
dictionary in an Irish corpus.
These are the five
most frequent patterns
in the subset of minor rules in
the corpus that I'm working on.
So I don't know
for a performance
that is interested in
playing this music.
Perhaps, the take away
of this is, OK, you
might want to start
studying these patterns
because they appear quite
often in the corpus.
So better to first master them.
For the future with
Michael, we want
to study how the
algorithm performs
in a nice corpus of
early music that he has,
and also, we want to analyze
some solos of Charlie Parker,
who was one of the most
mathematical improvisers
of the history.
And also for the
close future, I would
like to see if this tool can
be helpful for plagiarism
detection.
I suspect that two pieces
that are very similar
are also some similarities
in their pattern structure.
And that's all.
Thank you very much guys.
Any questions.
[APPLAUSE]
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
By the way, just
so you get a sense
for your final things,
that was 12 minutes.
So a tiny bit longer than
what you have as a maximum.
KIKI GUTIERREZ: Cool.
If any of you are interested
in a particular thing
of the algorithm,
just drop me an email,
and we can talk about it.
Thank you.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
So what I want to do
is I want to immediately
start by putting
some of these thoughts to work.
So get with a
partner next to you.
You can do that.
Over here, we need
a group of three.
Or unless you want
to participate
with a friend or jump over
there or jump over with Jordan,
if you do.
And here are six melodies.
I'm going to play
each one of them.
I'm going to play A
bunch of times also.
So I'll tell you which one I'm
playing, and you're going to--
and you can talk during this or
wait till just after playing.
You're going to
tell me which melody
is most or least similar to A.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
OK.
And this is B. And I
want you to say why.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
This is C.
And I'm going to
play A one more time
to get it back into our heads.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
And now D--
Oh, and by the way,
this isn't a right--
isn't a right answer one.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
Great.
Now E.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
And now A one more time before
doing F. So this is A again.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
And now F.
Oops, that's F and
E simultaneously,
which is very different.
Now F.
[PLAYING INSTRUMENT]
Great.
Talk amongst yourself.
I want a ranking
from your group,
so somebody write it down.
And I want to know why.
OK, let's bring it
all back together.
Let's bring it
So look looking at
your list, and we'll
count like normal human beings.
Whichever one is the
top in your list is one.
Whichever one
second, two, stuff.
And we'll vote by fingers first
off for the general ranking.
So if you hold up the
number of fingers that--
if it's closest, it's
pulled up one finger.
If not, two-- whatever.
And full palm means I
have no idea what that is.
OK, B. Oh, B's doing pretty well
A lot of twos, a couple of ones.
C. OK, well, a little
bit more variety.
Hold them up so that
other people can see also.
Look around the room.
It's not just for me.
Great.
D. Oh, OK, we got a variety
who don't know, whatever.
Great.
E. Oh, still see
some poems or things.
Great.
And F. OK.
Oh, we have one four.
Good, good.
What do you-- you put it down.
What do you guys--
those who put F as four,
what do you put as five?
AUDIENCE: D.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: B.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
D. OK, D. Good.
Good.
Great.
Somebody who had C above
B justify your answer.
Who had C above B?
There were a couple people.
Yeah, go ahead.
Jake first.
Yeah, groups.
AUDIENCE: C was basically just a
transposition, whereas B like--
B changed a lot of
the rhythms a bit.
B, I think, fits the exact
pitches a little better, but--
or aside from a couple places
where it has some accidentals,
but it changes the
rhythm quite a bit.
Whereas C is just
a transposition.
So for relative
pitch essentially.
We waited transposition
equivalence more.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: OK, good.
Good.
I'm already hearing words
that I'm liking stuff.
Great.
Somebody who had it the other
way around justify your answer.
Who had it the other way around?
Who had-- a bunch of people
had B above C. Yeah, John.
AUDIENCE: I'm looking for
the sound feel that A had.
Because a lot of the comments
are probably similar to A and B.
That's why we put it a
bit higher relative to C.
And when you take transposition
into account, only part of C's
becoming transpose,
so it doesn't even
feel like it's like
a full transposition.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Great.
Only part of it's transpose.
Yeah, yeah, it kind of
gets back on for a bit
and then comes back off.
Great.
Who had D-- who had D one two?
Anybody?
I can't remember.
Why do you have one or two?
AUDIENCE: Because it
basically has this--
so it has all of the same
notes in the right positions--
or basically--
yeah, all you have to
do is remove notes,
and then you get the
same thing, and--
I think with a few exceptions.
But that never happened
in any of them.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Great.
Who had D very low?
Yeah, go ahead, Tony.
AUDIENCE: Like before--
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Sorry, Tony.
Can you speak louder?
AUDIENCE: Before, like a
rhythm, I guess, the same.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: OK, great.
Did anybody have E above four?
OK.
AUDIENCE: We have D at three.
And we put it there because
the pattern was very similar,
if not identical,
even though the melody
wasn't all that close.
So we figured that probably
counted for something.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: So when
you say pattern, what's--
AUDIENCE: It's like the rhythm.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: The rhythm.
The rhythmic pattern,
it's about the same.
Good.
AUDIENCE: That's an
inversion, right?
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
Is it an inversion?
No.
Would I do that?
AUDIENCE: The inversion.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: By the way,
I can't remember where melody--
I think melody A comes from
a Huron book and then gives--
there's some search book, and
I should have my notes better,
and I'll try to make sure
it gets annotated later.
That had three other melodies.
I tried this in the past,
and it was so obvious
that everybody had the
exact same ranking.
I had to agree with them.
But I think this is better
for making some arguments.
Good.
Who had F anything but--
actually, somebody
who gave F five?
Jonathan, why would you--
did you give F five?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Why
did you give it five?
AUDIENCE: I mean, it didn't have
any noticeable similarities.
Like at first, it seemed
closer to E in terms of-- it
might have been inversion
but then not really.
The rhythm is also completely
different-- or not completely,
but it's fairly different.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Great.
So I'm just going to
point, and we'll get some--
just what your ranking is.
So say them from--
Matthew, what was yours?
AUDIENCE: Alphabetical order.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
B, C, D, E, F--
OK, good.
AUDIENCE: B, C, D, E, F.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: B, C, D, E, F.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: B,
C, E, D, F. Great.
Great.
Vincent?
AUDIENCE: C, B, D--
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
C, B, D-- good.
And anything it
feels like you're not
being represented on there?
Hannah, what's your group have?
AUDIENCE: I think we
put C, B, D, E, F.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: C, B,
D, E, F-- great, super.
Now what I want
you to do-- we're
not going to get through
all of the exercises today,
but I think this is the
most important part.
What I want you to do is
think about what ways--
I'll give you a
little bit of things--
what are some ways you can
make sure that your computer
system that is going to
classify things by similarity
follows your intuition
of what is similar,
and not somebody else's
intuition for what is similar?
So that's going to be the main
theme for the rest of this.
So we are intelligent people.
We are intelligent musicians.
We make these
choices, and yet we
are making differences on how
far and how similar they are.
So, in fact, I'm going
to blank the screen
and say the one takeaway
from today's lecture, I hope,
and from all these
things, is that there
is no right answer for the
similarity between two melodies,
between the similarity
between two pieces.
There may be wrong answers.
I will not deny that,
that if somebody
said that F was closer to, I
don't know, than the same thing
with one note
changed or something,
I would think that that might be
wrong, that your program might
be malfunctioning.
But there isn't a right answer.
And a lot of it--
what's different
between good answers
are what we think
of as important
when thinking similarity.
There is a yearly competition--
I think it's been
suspended since COVID,
so I don't know
if it's restarted,
but for the algorithm
that can classify songs
as the most similar.
And here is a place
where I would say,
what are your ground truths?
How do we trust that you
have gotten it right?
And are we just trying having
to recreate the views--
I won't say biases, but
the views of the people
who organize the conference and
what's that going to do for us?
So I want you to
start thinking that.
And I will tell you
what F is beforehand.
F is one that a lot of
computers' programs--
in fact, what I went aha
during one of these algorithms,
they could--
F is 1 that a number
of algorithms,
especially older ones, will
classify as the most similar.
Because what is F?
Unlike any of the other
lines, F has every single note
and every single rhythm,
if I did it right.
I was doing in my head.
Every single note and every
single rhythm from A--
just order didn't matter.
A is the counterset function,
the unordered version, the P--
yeah, the permutation does
not matter version of F.
Or F is the permutation does
not matter version of A.
Did I get it right?
AUDIENCE: It looks right.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: So
we're going to go quickly
through some things I
think you've probably
seen before, some ways
of measuring distance.
You all learned this at some
point, the Euclidean distance
between two points.
Take the square
root of the x terms.
root of the y term.
Add, what, difference squared
plus difference squared
square root.
Square root of x squared
plus difference between x
and difference between y.
So anyone seen this thing, where
the distance between these two
points, 3 comma 2
and 7 comma 8, is 10.
Taxicab distance--
Manhattan distance,
we'll go with taxicabs
since not all of us
have been to a Manhattan and had
the joys of taking a taxi there.
And so why this--
here, the distance was 10.
Here, it's approximately--
that's not a negative sign.
That's an approximate sign--
approximately 7.2.
Why is the distance
greater here?
Somebody who's done this
triangle inequality.
Talk English to me for a second.
Talk like you're talking
to your cab driver
who you're explaining to this--
cab drivers are really smart.
Talk, but who may not have
heard the final inequality.
What is represented
by the term Manhattan
distance or taxicab distance?
What's the notion-- intuition?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Go along the axes.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Go along
the axes or that go along--
let's get more literal.
One of the things that
we don't do so well
is step back into
the real world.
What is the distance traveled?
What constrains the taxicab
from not hitting distance of 7.2
but instead of 10?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You get straight
up and down to the side.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: You
can only go straight
up and down to the side.
You can only go on-- let's
go even further back.
What, in Manhattan, if you
don't want to get arrested,
you can only drive on?
AUDIENCE: Streets.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Streets.
And the streets
in Manhattan go--
AUDIENCE: Orthogonal.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Yeah,
they're orthogonal.
There are these little lines.
So you are constrained
in where you can go.
So if there are constraints
on your distance,
and the most common one is you
can go up, down, left, or right.
You can't always do that
in Manhattan but because
of one ways.
But let's assume that we
have certain constraints.
You can be brought down.
Good.
I wanted to make sure
that we all have that,
and so that we can
start thinking about--
first off, that what
operations are allowed
determines the distance metric.
What operations are
allowed determines
how far the distance are.
What are some operations
we do in music?
That's a question.
What operations do we
allow and not allow?
Adam?
AUDIENCE: We could look
at many different models.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: We can look at
midi difference between notes.
So therefore, we can take notes
and bring them higher and lower.
We can raise and lower notes.
What are other things we can do?
What are some things you've
ever done with a piece
to make it a little bit
different or interesting?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You can
subdivide or combine notes.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: You can
Maybe you can, maybe you can't.
But yeah, quite often you can.
This is a context where you can.
Yeah, other--
AUDIENCE: --durations.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: You can
change durations-- great, super.
How about this?
Which of these two chords
are closer to the first one?
The first one is going
to be C major versus--
another little
similarity problem.
The second one was G major.
Sorry, the first
one was G major.
The second one, I went from
C major to C augmented.
Great, C augmented triad.
So those are two things.
Which one?
Who votes that from going from
C major to G major is closer?
Who votes that C major and
C augmented are closer?
Two people.
OK, great.
So a lot of it has to do
with your thought about--
well, on the augmented,
you're only changing one note,
and you're only changing by a
half step, the minimum distance
in our Manhattanized musical
world of midi and piano
keyboards.
That is, their minimum
distance is one half step--
not for all music in the world.
Great.
C major to G major--
you're also just moving one.
If you think of
something this way,
you're moving one
distance in what space?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
Oh, what's that word?
AUDIENCE: Circle of fifths.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: It's
circle of fifths space.
C and G are about
as close as you
can get without
being the identity,
C and F probably the other
way, although, I don't know,
maybe it's a one way
circle of fifths.
You only go around one
direction or another.
Great.
Based on the time,
I'm not going to go
through all these other
measurements of distance
that people can do.
Who has heard of
earthmover distance?
That is the amount
of work that it
takes to move one mound of
things over to another place.
And sometimes, you're
optimizing depending
on how much it costs
to move distance
and how much it costs
to move material.
You can end up with
different results.
This was one of
the charts I think
I showed early in the
semester is here's
one place where
earthmover distance might
be a good use of
things of distances.
And then Levenshtein
or edit distance
is what was mentioned in--
do you use it in your work?
Yep, so that's where
you're talking about,
so the idea of how to change
the word Hyundai into Honda,
and no international East Asian
politics please for a second.
And you can think of every
time, OK, H and H are the same.
So it has a cost of 0.
Or we can delete the H and start
an O, and we have a cost of 1.
But we can find the
pattern of as we
change, we're going to
insert a Y after the H.
We're going to
substitute a U for an O.
This should be
symmetrical the other way
around-- different operations.
N is the same, so that's good.
D is the same, so it
doesn't cost anything.
So our cost function goes here.
And so we're trying to find
the minimum cost from going
from one end to another.
We don't have time to go through
all of the algorithms for this.
But Levenshtein
distance, edit distance,
has a lot of good
qualities that makes
it useful for a lot of
musical similarity tasks.
Just so that you can
say your professor
at least put the algorithm
up on the hand for a second.
But more importantly,
I think a lot of times
is thinking about the
particular costs of things
in a musical space,
in a musical world.
So for instance,
is deleting what--
we're trying to think about
two pieces, two melodies.
One of them deletes
the first note.
What would you call
the cost on that?
Well, maybe 1.
But then, if it doesn't make
up the total rhythm later,
and everything from here
on is going to be off,
and it's one line within
an orchestral piece,
that might be a higher
cost, maybe some--
and the classic debate
is whether changing
a note is that the same
or changing a letter
in something like this?
Is this the same?
Does this cost 1
or does this cost--
well, one way you can change
a letter is you delete it,
and then you add a new
letter back with a cost of 2.
And these are things
that come up quite a bit
in similarity search.
And just really want to say that
it comes up a lot in music--
don't borrow your distance
metric from somebody else.
Different ones might be used
for different situations.
So the distance
between dog and gato--
well, we can substitute d for g.
I don't know, or maybe
we add other things.
But I'm going to assert
that, in some situations,
the distance might be
2 between dog and gato.
What we do is we use the
substitute closely related
pet function for cost of 1.
So dog becomes cat, and then
translate English to Spanish
might cost 1.
And if you think about
large language learning
models and things,
you might want
to have functions like this.
And, in fact, this is not a
digital humanities text class.
But if it were and we
were doing computation,
we'd definitely be talking about
an algorithm called word2vec,
which was one of the earlier
successful algorithms
for trying to predict what words
are similar to other words, what
words are synonyms, so you can
create a kind of cost function
that is for this word is a
synonym for this one that
has been substituted
that is lower than this--
then this sentence is
different from this one
because it's using a
completely different concept.
I'll skip that.
So when we're thinking
about these distances
and these weird things
like substitute dog for cat
on low-cost substitute
cat for gato
at low cost, what's the term
that we spent a lot of time,
maybe even too much
time for-- it felt
like at the time-- talking about
earlier in this semester, that
helps to think about things
that are not the same,
but might be closely
related to each other?
AUDIENCE: Equivalence.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Equivalence,
or equivalence classes, yes.
So one of the things
you might want to do
is define what equivalence
classes it could be.
I mean, I think last--
other times, I've given the
exact same melody up an octave,
and everybody
immediately said, oh,
that is basically
the same thing.
So everybody was
very quickly putting
in an oh, equivalence
class things.
So I wanted to make
sure that we had that.
And so once you have
these distances,
we tend to go through-- and this
is if you're in a biology class,
you'll spend a lot of
computational biology,
a lot of time on this--
sequence alignment,
a kind of distance
metric where you're
trying to find the minimum
distance between two things
that you believe might represent
the same type of thing.
Or you might say it's
innocent until proven guilty.
We'll first try to see if they
can be changed into another
thing at a low cost and then
discard once we realize the cost
cannot be minimized.
I will say that algorithms that
can be short circuited, that you
can prove at a certain
point you can't
do better than this cost will
speed up a lot of your run times
because once--
you might say that
there's no way
that this could be better than
20% or it could be-- yeah,
there's no way that this could
possibly be better than 90%
similar to this.
So I'm going to stop looking
at the rest of the piece
or whatever your cut off.
So one of the classic things
for sequence alignment
is trying to find--
this is Google's data
set they released
at the height of Britney
Spears popularity of all
the number of searches
that they believed
were trying to find the top
left one, Britney Spears--
actually really,
really impressed
that the number of correct
spellings of a hard name
to spell outweighs the rest.
Anyhow, that's
all we're talking.
And the people who are
really, really good
at this-- and any time
I'm trying to figure out
a similarity sequence
alignment or a similarity task
that I don't know is to
look at the people who
are trying to align
base pairs in biology
or trying to align genes because
they have many, many options.
So I'm just going
to keep pounding
this term in as many
different ways I can do.
All the things that
we're just working with--
Hyundai, Honda, Britney Spears,
genes, those are all strings.
But we work on notes and clefs
and things like notes and stuff,
but things like that.
So how do we get them in?
So this is great to get this
from two different people,
same thing-- we use
things called hashes,
which are very similar to
the concept of viewpoints
to the rescue, so that--
try to convert things--
hash and note.
We might say that here are
equivalence classes all notes
that are names with octave.
And so we might hash a stream by
just joining all the hash notes
for all the notes in there.
You will find, in Music 21,
if you're working on it,
there's a bunch of
tools for this already.
They're in
music21.search, a module
that we have not
talked about now
and we will not
talk about again.
But if you're doing
a lot of searching,
it's probably worth reading
the module reference for it.
I think that there
might be a user's guide,
but I can't remember
if I finished it
or if it just trails
off after a few words.
So we might take a string,
convert it to a stream--
that's hard to say very fast--
and translate it.
And we might have
some of hash function
that tries to make everything
into an ASCII character.
Though there's no
reason that everything
needs to be turned into a
string like nameWithOctave.
In a lot of ways, strings
are just arrays of ints.
We're talking about that A--
no, lowercase a is generally
represented internally
as anyone-- remember number?
AUDIENCE: 97.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: What's that?
97 or 96, I can't remember.
96?
Yep, and capital
A-- is that one 60--
AUDIENCE: 65.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: 65.
OK, so some people
some people know these.
I used to have them
all top of the head.
So all the letters
you're doing have
a particular representation.
And back in the bad, bad days
of the '60s and '70s, different
computers would have different
representations for this,
and then we all agreed on the
same representation for letters.
And then we remembered that
there are other things in the--
other characters in the world.
That looks too much
like an A. How do I
do a jin or something, or an
alpha, beta, things like that.
And then, for a while,
we had a big problem
that they weren't all
converging to the same thing.
Anyhow, digression aside,
maybe we'll get to the point
where we can start converting
things besides midi numbers
and notes into something
more standardized
because, right now, the
midi numbers is basically
the only standardized
notes, which is probably
why midi keeps being used for a
lot of computational projects.
So the hard part is
always finding out
what numbers we should
use to represent a note.
So if we're going to
convert nameWithOctave
and we want to make
a string, and then
we want to make it
a number, and then
we want to have a
whole bunch of numbers,
what have we just recently
seen that looks like a tool
to take a score or
a part or something
and works like a
hash or a viewpoint
that tries to convert it
to a bunch of numbers?
Not asking you to think too
far back, but farther back
than today.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I'm getting a
feature representation.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT:
Yeah, extracting
features, getting a
feature representation.
Yeah, so feature
extraction and this kind
of viewpoint searching go
hand-in-hand with each other.
So if it's partially why once
you finish up a search function,
you're just going to
want to probably try
to see if AI or machine
learning can do it
better because you have
everything ready to go for it.
But sometimes what we extract
is different from others.
I want to give a little bit
of a caution that back then--
of course, you had
to do a little final,
a final project called the UAP--
and we thought that
making these viewpoints,
making a hashing system for
Music 21 for comparisons
would be a nice senior project.
And then we both
realized that, no,
it's a lot bigger than we
thought and a lot more complex
than we thought, and so
it needed to be an M. Eng.
Emily Zhang was great at
creating this and great,
oh, we did a really
great M. Eng project.
And then we realized,
no, this really
needs to be a PhD project.
We did not continue on--
there are so many difficult
parts of hash algorithms
because you want to
think about things like--
yeah, we'll not get to it--
going all the way
back to the beginning,
how can we create a
viewpoint or something
that allows D not to be totally,
totally different for anybody
who didn't put D as the last
of all possible results?
What kinds of hashes--
what kinds of numbers would we
need to represent a piece on
to make D not the worst
and really make sure
that F isn't the best?
So that's going to be our
last 5-6 minutes of class.
I want you to talk with 5
minutes of y'all talking with
each other, and 5 minutes of
y'all talk and talking to me.
So what kinds of
feature extraction,
what kind of hash function,
what kind of viewpoints?
These are all slightly
different concepts,
but they're all
in the same area.
What kinds of
equivalence classes
will you need in order
to make this happen?
Go ahead.
OK, I hear words continuing
but less frequently.
Let's talk about what
are some of the ways
that people thought to create
a strategy that doesn't
make D and F about the same?
Yeah, go ahead.
AUDIENCE: You could look at
the sequence of local maxima
and minima.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Local
maxima and minima.
OK, I think I know what
you're talking about,
but let's give you
a little example.
Let's talk about
A. What do you--
AUDIENCE: So you
could maybe argue
that the C is the
local minima, and then
the F is higher than both of its
neighbors, so it's a maximum.
And then a D is a minimum,
the E's a maximum,
and then the D and C after that
are not really anything until
you hit the A on the 16th note.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Cool.
So yeah, we're just
looking at every time
the direction changes
of the pitches.
Great.
And compare that-- so beginning
A has G, F, D, E. Here,
we have D, F, G--
a tiny bit different, D,
F, but then going down to--
a little bit different,
but it's at least
giving some numbers we have.
Always the question is,
does your current streak
end when you hit a rest or not?
And maybe it depends on how
long the rest is, so good.
Other strategies?
Adam?
AUDIENCE: I would look at
where offsets are the same
and then check that their
notes are the same or not.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Great.
So we're going to look at
offsets that are the same
and see if notes
are the same or not.
That works really well.
And what I'd love to do, if
this were, what do you call it,
the generalized
adversarial problem
set, the gain problem
set, where one team
has to solve the problem.
The other team has
to keep giving them
things that break that.
I think it was a great idea.
And I think it would
work in general.
But I could generate something
where all I insert is
let's insert a 64th rest at
the beginning and then put all
random notes.
And you're going
to end up with--
and then maybe we'll put one
note that's the same at the end.
And you could end up with 100%
of the notes on the same offset
are the same.
I think we would really
work in the real world,
but we might want to always
think about something like that,
too.
Great idea.
John?
Then two people.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] so first--
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: You can say--
AUDIENCE: --builds
up on what Adam said
AUDIENCE: But first, you
take a look at the notes
and do a set, kind of like
crossover between a set of D's
and aces and then ASes.
So both of those would still
show up relatively high.
And then compare
the offsets, which
would obviously take
up a bit, but still
keep D relatively high.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Super.
When we're talking about
offsets, are we talking about--
what kind of offsets?
AUDIENCE: We're in the--
I guess within the two
measures that the notes being--
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Great.
Where in the two measures?
Where in the measure?
We sometimes want to do global
offset from the beginning
of the measure.
But then you can't identify
similar phrases or, all it takes
is put a repeat, put the first
four measures, repeat it once,
and suddenly the whole rest
of the piece is different.
So yeah, that's great.
AUDIENCE: If you
just start at time
equals 0 and go all the
way through the piece,
like anytime the two pieces
have the same pitch, you score--
so the alpha that they
both have on beat two
would be like a
quarter point because--
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: The F that
they both have on beat two
would be a quarter
point because--
AUDIENCE: Their duration
is only for that 16th note.
MICHAEL CUTHBERT: Got you.
So we look at shared duration.
Great.
I like that a lot.
Did anybody try to come
up with a equivalent?
Yeah?
The contour ends up being a
kind of a new equivalence class
that we hadn't talked about,
which kind of works out
in thinking that everything
that doesn't change directions
is a kind of passing tone, even
though not in the proper music
theory term, and
so can be ignored.
By the way, the one
I use quite often
is I'm just going to look
on downbeats or on beats
and ignore everything else,
and that works pretty well
for a lot of things.